I owe everything to George Bailey.
Help him, dear Father.
Joseph, Jesus and Mary,
help my friend Mr. Bailey.
Help my son George tonight.
He never thinks about himself, God.
That's why he's in trouble.
George is a good guy.
Give him a break, God.
I love him, dear Lord.
Watch over him tonight.
Please, God.
Something's the matter with Daddy.
Please bring Daddy back.
Please bring Daddy home.
Watch over him tonight.
Please bring Daddy back.
Hello, Joseph. Trouble?
to send someone down.
for a man named George Bailey.
George Bailey?
You're right.
immediately. Whose turn is it?
That's why I came to see you, sir.
It's that clockmaker's turn again.
Hasn't got his wings yet, has he?
We've passed him up right along.
he's got the IQ of a rabbit.
the faith of a child. Simple.
Joseph, send for Clarence.
You sent for me, sir?
A man down on Earth needs our help.
Splendid. Is he sick?
No, worse. He's discouraged.
At exactly 10:45 p.m. Earth time,
that man will be thinking seriously
of throwing away God's greatest gift.
Then I've only an hour to dress.
What are they wearing now?
getting acquainted with George Bailey.
Sir, if I should accomplish this mission,
I mean, might I perhaps win my wings?
for over 200 years now, sir,
and people are beginning to talk.
What's that book you've got there?
The Adventures of Tom Sawyer.
with George Bailey
and you'll get your wings.
Oh, thank you, sir. Thank you.
Poor George. Sit down.
Sit down? What are we...
If you're going to help a man,
don't you?
Well, naturally, of course. I...
Now, keep your eyes open.
See the town?
Where? l don't see a thing.
You haven't got your wings yet.
Concentrate.
Begin to see something?
Why, yes. This is amazing.
you'll see all by yourself.
Oh, wonderful.
Yay! Yippee!
Okay, boys, let's go.
Hey, who's that?
That's your problem. George Bailey.
A boy?
back in 1919.
you'll have to remember later on.
Come on, Marty.
Let's go, Marty!
Attaboy, Marty.
Hee-haw!
Let's go, Sam. Hee-haw, Sammy!
my kid brother Harry Bailey.
I'm not scared.
Come on, Harry.
Let's go, Harry!
Come on, Harry!
-Come on, Harry!
Help, George, help!
Help!
Don't worry, Harry. I'm coming!
-Hang on, Harry!
-Make a chain, gang.
George saved his brother's life that day,
which infected his left ear.
Cost him his hearing in that ear.
before he was able to go back
at old man Gower's drugstore.
Mr. Potter.
Who's that, a king?
That's Henry F. Potter,
in the county.
-Hee-haw! Hee-haw!
Go to work, slave.
Don't worry, we'll take care of it.
Wish I had a million dollars.
Hot dog!
It's me, Mr. Gower. George Bailey.
You're late.
Yes, sir.
Hello, George.
Hello, Mary.
Hello, Violet.
Two cents' worth of shoelaces?
She was here first.
I'm still thinking.
Shoelaces?
Please, Georgie.
I like him.
You like every boy.
What's wrong with that?
Here you are.
Help me down?
Help you down?
Made up your mind yet?
I'll take chocolate.
-I don't like coconuts.
You don't like coconuts?
where coconuts come from?
Lookit here.
the Coral Sea.
A new magazine. I never saw it before.
Only us explorers can get it.
in the National Geographic Society.
Is this the ear you can't hear on?
I'll love you till the day I die.
You watch.
and maybe three or four wives.
Wait and see.
-Yes, sir?
You're not paid to be a canary.
No, sir.
Anything?
No.
-No.
I'll get them, sir.
over to Mrs. Blaine.
She's waiting for them.
Yes, sir.
haven't they, sir?
Yeah.
Is it a charge, sir?
Yes, George.
Mr. Gower, I...
-Yes, sir.
Where you heading?
-Some other time, George.
-There's a squall in there.
It's shaping up into a storm.
-Who is it?
-Bank examiner?
I should have called him yesterday.
Switch it inside.
I'm not crying, Mr. Potter.
That's a whole lot worse.
All I'm asking for is 30 days more.
-Just a minute, Son.
I'll dig up that $5,000 somehow.
-Pop.
-Have you put any real pressure
to pay those mortgages?
A lot of these people are out of work.
Well, then, foreclose.
These families have children.
-They're not my children.
Mr. Potter.
or a charity ward?
-Not with my money.
such a hard-skulled character?
You have no family, no children.
to spend all the money you've got.
to miserable failures
to spend for me.
He's not a failure!
-George, George. Quiet, George.
You're the biggest man in town...
-...bigger than him,
-Gives you an idea of the Baileys.
Don't let him say that about you, Pop.
All right, Son. All right. Thanks.
I'll talk to you tonight.
What?
been there an hour ago.
Mrs. Blaine.
Where's Mrs. Blaine's box of capsules?
I... You...
Didn't you hear what I said?
Yes, sir. I...
are you playing anyway?
Why didn't you deliver them right away?
Don't you know that boy's very sick?
You're hurting my sore ear.
You lazy loafer.
you don't know what you're doing.
in those capsules.
I know you're unhappy.
You got the telegram, and you're upset.
in those capsules.
It wasn't your fault, Mr. Gower.
Just look and see what you did.
it's poison.
I tell you, it's poison.
I know you feel bad.
-Don't hurt my sore ear again!
-Oh, no, no. Oh, George, George.
Oh, Mr. Gower, I won't ever tell anyone.
I know how you're feeling.
Hope to die, I won't.
Oh, George. George.
Genuine English cowhide.
Combination lock.
-Nope, nope, nope, nope.
Now, look, Joe. Now, look.
I want a big one.
What did you stop it for?
at that face.
Who is it?
George Bailey.
slapped back by the druggist?
That's the kid.
It's a good face. I like it.
I like George Bailey.
did he ever tell anyone about the pills?
Not a soul.
Did he ever go exploring?
Well, wait and see.
Big, see? I don't want one for one night.
I want something for 1,001 nights
from Italy and Baghdad, Samarkand.
Great big thing, about...
-Yeah.
this old secondhand job, would you?
Now you're talking.
in case the boat sunk.
-No charge.
It sounded like you said "no charge."
That's right.
Well, what's my name doing on it?
Came down and picked it out himself.
My old boss. Isn't that nice?
What boat are you sailing on?
I'm working across on a cattle boat.
-Okay, I like cows.
Hello, Mr. Gower. How are you?
It's just exactly what I wanted.
Forget it.
-Hope you enjoy it.
I wish I had a million dollars.
Hot dog!
Avast there, Captain Cook!
picture postcards, will you, George?
don't take any plug nickels.
Hey, George, your suitcase is leaking.
Hey, Ernie!
-Hiya, George.
-Hey, I'm a rich tourist today.
How about driving me home in style?
-Yes, sir.
I put on my hat.
Good afternoon, Mr. Bailey.
Hello, Violet.
That's some dress you got on there.
This old thing?
when I don't care how I look.
-Yes.
We'll show you the town.
No, thanks.
and see what the wife's doing.
Family man.
you're shaking the house down.
Stop it.
I wish I was up there with them.
George!
That's why all children should be girls.
there wouldn't be any... Oh, never mind.
come down to dinner this minute.
how long we've been waiting for you.
-Okay, Ma.
-Ta-da!
-There you are.
Oh, you two idiots.
George, sit down and have dinner.
-I've eaten.
for your graduating party? Look at you!
I don't care. It's George's tux.
have you got those pies?
I'll hit you with this broom!
There's a moon out tonight.
in the old Bailey boarding house.
Oh, my lands, my blood pressure.
take over a lot of plates and things.
What plates?
of the Eats Committee.
We only need a couple of dozen.
Now, not my best Haviland, no.
Oh, let him have the plates, Mother.
Uncle Billy and I are gonna miss you.
I'm gonna miss you, too, Pop.
What's the matter? You look tired.
I had another tussle with Potter today.
on the board of directors,
he'd ease up on us a little bit.
money-grubbing buzzard anyway?
sick in his mind.
Sick in his soul, if he has one.
that has anything that he can't have.
He hates us mostly, I guess.
Gangway. Gangway.
-So long.
-Very funny, very funny.
Put those things in the car,
for you. Now, hurry up.
-Now, don't drop one of those.
You coming later, George?
and be bored to death?
Lots of pretty girls,
that new floor tonight, too.
-No gin tonight, Son.
Oh, Pop, just a little?
No, Son. Not one drop.
Boys and girls and music.
Why do they need gin?
when I graduated from high school?
Pretty much.
we could send Harry to college with you.
half the night.
We have that all figured out.
at the Building and Loan,
work there for four years, then he'll go.
Pretty young for that job.
Well, no younger than I was.
Well, you were born older, George.
How's that?
I said you were born older.
what you want to do
when you get out of college.
what I've always talked about,
plan modern cities.
All that stuff I've been talking about.
before you're 30?
I'll settle for half that in cash.
Of course, it's just a hope.
But you wouldn't consider coming back
to the Building and Loan, would you?
Well, I... I...
Then you'd be more comfortable,
that's going on.
I'd hear anything worth listening to.
You would, eh?
I know it's soon to talk about it.
No, now, Pop, I couldn't.
for the rest of my life
in a shabby little office.
I'm sorry, Pop. I didn't mean that, but I...
It's this business of nickels and dimes
trying to figure out
on a length of pipe.
and something important.
I feel that, in a small way,
we're doing something important,
satisfying a fundamental urge.
his own roof and walls and fireplace.
And we're helping him get those things
in our shabby little office.
I know, Pop. I know that.
I wish I felt that...
like a miser here in order to...
have already finished college.
I'd bust.
Yes, yes, you're right, Son.
You see what I mean, don't you, Pop?
This town is no place for any man
unless he's willing to crawl to Potter.
Now, you've got talent, Son. I've seen it.
and get out of here.
Pop, you want a shock?
I think you're a great guy.
-I heard it.
one of you lunkheads said it.
I'm gonna miss old Annie.
and go over to Harry's party.
Have a good time, Son.
Excuse me.
There you are.
George, hello.
You know my kid brother George.
-Hello, George.
Hee-haw!
Sam Wainwright.
How are you? When did you get here?
I thought I'd give the kids a treat.
Old college graduate now.
they call me.
you're gonna make it after all, huh?
-Hello, Sam.
-He has?
and his mouth's watering.
if you're gonna come along with us.
Well, I got to make some dough first.
We need great ends like you.
Not broken down old guys like this one.
Hee-haw!
George, welcome back.
Hello, Mr. Partridge, how are you?
a great idea.
Saved us another building.
Now, Harry, Sam, have a lot of fun.
and drink. Lots of pretty girls around.
A third dance... A third...
-Hello. What am I bid?
George.
Marty! Well, it's old home week.
-Sam, Harry, how are you?
-What's that?
-Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Mama wants you." Remember?
Dance with her, will you?
already with all these kids.
Come on, be a sport.
give her the thrill of her life. Hey, Sis!
Don't be long, Marty.
I'm not being a wet nurse to a...
some guy came up and tripped me.
That's the reason why I came in fourth.
that race'd have been a cinch.
but I couldn't find out.
because they'd be scared.
what kind of a guy I am.
You remember George. This is Mary.
Well, I'll be seeing you.
Well, well, well.
Now to get back to my story, see?
Hey, this is my dance.
Why don't you stop annoying people?
Well, I'm sorry. Hey!
-Hello.
You look at me as if you didn't know me.
Well, I don't.
almost every day.
Me?
named Mary Hatch. That wasn't you.
The big Charleston contest!
The prize, a genuine loving cup.
will remain on the floor.
Let's go!
I'm not very good at this.
Neither am I.
Okay. What can we lose?
Hey, you're wonderful.
What's the matter, Othello? Jealous?
under this floor?
causes this floor to open up?
that George Bailey
is dancing right over that crack?
And I've got the key.
Stand back, everybody! Stand back!
They're cheering us. We must be good.
Get out of there!
What... Oh, well.
can't you come out tonight?
Can't you come out tonight?
Buffalo gals, can't you come out tonight
And dance
By the light
Of the moon?
-Beautiful.
I'd be bored to death.
the commotion in that locker room.
to get this stuff we're wearing here.
Let me hold that old wet dress of yours.
Do I look as funny as you do?
I guess I'm not quite the football type.
You look wonderful!
You know, if it wasn't me talking,
the prettiest girl in town.
Well, why don't you say it?
How old are you anyway?
Eighteen.
you were seventeen.
Too young or too old?
Oh, no, no. Just right. Your age fits you.
without your clothes on.
I mean, without a dress you look older.
I mean younger. You look... You just...
I'm on the thing here.
Sir, my train, please.
A pox upon me for a clumsy lout.
Your caboose, milady.
You may kiss my hand.
Hey.
Hey, Mary.
As I was lumberin' down the street
Down the street, down the street
at the old Granville house.
Oh, no, don't. I love that old house.
and then try and break some glass.
a pretty good shot nowadays, too.
It's full of romance, that old place.
I'd like to live in it.
In that place?
Now, watch.
Right in the second floor, there. See?
What did you wish, George?
Not just one wish, a whole hatful.
I'm gonna do tomorrow
and the year after that.
of this crummy little town off my feet,
and I'm gonna see the world!
the Coliseum.
to college to see what they know.
And then I'm gonna build things.
I'm gonna build airfields.
100 stories high.
I'm gonna build bridges a mile long.
What, are you gonna throw a rock?
Hey, that's pretty good.
What did you wish, Mary?
can't you come out tonight?
Can't you come out tonight?
Buffalo gals, can't you come out tonight
And
Dance by the light of the moon?
when you threw that rock?
-Come on, tell me.
If I told you, it might not come true.
What is it you want, Mary?
What do you want? You want the moon?
around it and pull it down.
I'll give you the moon, Mary.
I'll take it.
Then what?
and it would all dissolve, see?
of your fingers and your toes
and the ends of your hair.
-Yes!
instead of talking her to death?
How's that?
You want me to kiss her, huh?
Youth is wasted on the wrong people.
Come on back out here!
hair back on your head. What are you...
Mary?
Okay, I give up. Where are you?
Over here in the hydrangea bushes.
Here you are. Catch.
Wait a minute. What am I doing?
This is a very interesting situation.
Please give me my robe.
like this every day.
I'd like to have my robe.
Not in Bedford Falls, anyway.
-Gesundheit.
-This requires a little thought here.
Give me my robe.
but I've never...
I'm gonna tell your mother on you.
My mother's way up on the corner there.
I'll call the police.
They'd be on my side, too.
Then I'm going to scream!
Maybe I could sell tickets.
Let's see. No, the point is
in order to get this robe... I've got it.
I'll make a deal with you, Mary.
George! George!
George, come on home! Quick!
-What?
-Come on, George, let's hurry.
-Yes.
Campbell's there now.
we'll need you for, George.
-I have a taxi waiting downstairs.
that George gave up his trip to Europe
these past few months.
Good luck to you at school, George.
-Goodbye, George.
of this meeting,
to our dear friend Peter Bailey.
I'd like to get to my real purpose.
-Wait for what?
is not necessary to this town.
a motion to dissolve this institution
over to the receiver.
I'll wring his neck.
what that buzzard...
Mr. Chairman.
It's too soon after Peter Bailey's death
the Building and Loan.
Peter Bailey died three months ago.
I second Mr. Potter's motion.
Very well. In that case,
to withdraw. But before you go,
to express its deep sorrow
-Thank you very much.
It was his faith and devotion
for this organization.
I'll go further than that.
Peter Bailey was the Building and Loan.
That's fine, Potter, coming from you,
drove him to his grave.
Peter Bailey was not a businessman.
That's what killed him.
God rest his soul.
He was a man of high ideals, so-called.
can ruin this town.
to Ernie Bishop,
that fellow that sits around all day
on his brains in his taxi, you know.
the bank turned down this loan.
But he comes here,
a house worth $5,000.
-Well, I handled that, Mr. Potter.
His salary, insurance.
I can personally vouch for his character.
-Yes, sir.
with some employee here,
you can come and borrow money.
What does that get us?
A discontented, lazy rabble
instead of a thrifty working class.
a few starry-eyed dreamers
and fill their heads
with a lot of impossible ideas.
Now, I say...
Now, hold on, Mr. Potter.
was no businessman. I know that.
penny-ante Building and Loan
I'll never know.
can say anything against his character,
because his whole life was...
and Uncle Billy started this thing,
Isn't that right, Uncle Billy?
to send Harry to school, let alone me.
get out of your slums, Mr. Potter.
Why, here, you're all businessmen here.
doesn't it make them better customers?
What'd you say just a minute ago?
They had to wait and save their money
of a decent home.
Wait? Wait for what?
and leave them?
and broken-down that they...
a working man to save $5,000?
that this rabble you're talking about,
and living and dying in this community.
and pay and live and die
in a couple of decent rooms and a bath?
Anyway, my father didn't think so.
but to you,
they're cattle.
a much richer man than you'll ever be.
I'm not interested in your book.
I'm talking about the Building and Loan.
what you're talking about.
you can't get your fingers on,
That's what you're talking about, I know.
Well, I've said too much. I...
You do what you want with this thing.
There's just one thing more, though.
this measly one-horse institution
can come without crawling to Potter.
Come on, Uncle Billy.
Sentimental hogwash. I want my motion.
George, old boy.
You should have heard him.
We heard a lot of yelling.
out of business after 25 years.
-Here it is. "Help wanted. Female."
to hang around, George?
-Yeah, hey, you'll miss your train.
Go on.
-Never mind. Don't worry about that.
So what? I can get another job.
-56.
Hey, look, you gave up your boat trip,
too, do you?
They voted Potter down.
They want to keep it going.
You did it, George. You did it.
only one condition.
-And that's the best part of it.
as Executive Secretary
to take his father's place.
-You can keep him on. That's all right.
you can hire anyone you like.
this thing straight. I'm leaving.
I'm going to school.
Uncle Billy here, he's your man.
they'll vote with Potter otherwise.
-That's right.
his school money to his brother, Harry,
and sent him to college.
Harry became a football star.
Made second team all-American.
Yeah, but what happened to George?
waiting for Harry to come back
and take over the Building and Loans.
for somebody that likes to travel.
Look at this. Here.
man with construction experience."
Here's the Yukon, right here.
man with engineering experience."
There she blows.
sounds in the world are?
Lunch is served. Dinner...
plane motors and train whistles.
-There's the professor now.
all-American Bailey.
"Geographic Explorer" Bailey.
Uncle Billy, you haven't changed a bit.
you know that.
Oh, am I glad to see you.
-She's home, cooking the fatted calf.
-Oh, wait! Wait, wait a minute.
I want you to meet Ruth.
-How do you do?
-Ruth Dakin Bailey, if you don't mind.
-Well, I wired you I had a surprise.
Here she is. Meet the wife.
Well, what do you know? A wife.
-How do you do?
What am I doing? Congratulations!
-They're married!
Why don't you tell somebody?
I can't wait to see everybody's reaction.
-Why, yes.
What's a pretty girl like you doing
of mine?
My father offered him a job.
Well, Harry's cup runneth over.
out of turn. I never said I'd take it.
for four years, and,
I would like to...
I'll be right back.
It was a surprise to me.
my nephew's wife.
-Old, old friend of the Baileys.
Let's see...
I've heard him speak of you.
we're gonna give the biggest party
this town ever saw.
Here, have some popcorn.
That's all Harry ever talks about.
Ruth, this...
What about this job?
in Buffalo.
in the research business.
-Oh, yes, very.
but good future, you know.
-Harry's a genius at research.
-And you did, too.
Hey, Joe.
I feel so good.
I think I will. I think I will.
What did you say? Huh?
Maybe I'd better go home.
Where's my hat? Where's my...
-The middle one.
Oh boy, oh boy. Now, look,
Would you do that, George?
Right down here.
Old Building and Loan pal, huh?
and then right straight down there.
Oh, that way, huh?
My wild Irish rose
I'm all right. I'm all right.
The sweetest flower I know
Hello, Ma.
That's for nothing.
-She's swell, isn't she?
she can keep Harry on his toes.
Keep him out of Bedford Falls, anyway.
is back from school?
Came back three days ago.
Nice girl, Mary.
find the answers, George.
Stop that grunting.
why you shouldn't call on Mary?
Sure. Sam Wainwright.
-Yes, Sam's crazy about Mary.
-Well, how do you know?
-No.
-Well, I've got eyes, haven't I?
whenever you're around.
Sam Wainwright's away in New York,
-And all's fair in love and war.
I don't know about war.
you right to your back-collar button.
Trying to get rid of me, huh?
What's your hurry?
old Building and Loan pal,
and do a little passionate necking.
Oh, George.
in the right direction...
This direction.
Good night, Mrs. Bailey.
-Now, wait a minute.
I think I got a date.
just in case, huh?
We'll wait for you, baby.
-Hello Vi.
-Nothing.
Where are you going?
down at the library.
ofjust reading about things?
Yes.
-Not a thing.
Let's make a night of it.
I'd love it, Georgie. What'll we do?
and take off our shoes
-Huh?
It's beautiful up there in the moonlight,
and we can swim in it.
and smell the pines
against the peaks,
and we'll stay up there the whole night,
There'll be a terrific scandal.
Why, walk in the grass in my bare feet?
Why it's 10 miles up to Mount Bedford.
-Okay, just forget about the whole thing.
-Hello, Mary.
I just happened to be passing by here.
Yes, so I noticed.
-How's that?
-About what?
About coming in.
and said you were on your way over
-My mother just called you?
Well, how did she know?
-I didn't tell anybody.
and happened to be passing by here.
What do you...
Went for a walk. That's all.
-All right, dear.
Well, are you coming in or aren't you?
Well, I'll come in for a minute.
But I...
I was coming over here, you know.
-Tuesday.
Where did you get that dress?
-It's all right.
to New York,
and the rest of them.
but I don't know.
I guess I was homesick.
Homesick? For Bedford Falls?
Yes, and my family and...
Everything.
Would you like to sit down?
All right, for a minute.
I still can't understand it, though.
I was coming here.
Would you rather leave?
No. I don't want to be rude.
Well, then, sit down.
What's that?
Some joke, huh?
Well...
around here.
Thank you.
And dance by the
What's the matter?
Oh. Oh, yeah, yeah.
Well...
and Ruth, isn't it?
Oh, yeah, yeah, that's all right.
Don't you like her?
She's a peach.
you're not enthusiastic about, huh?
for Harry and Marty and Sam and you.
Mary! Mary!
Who's down there with you?
It's George Bailey, Mother.
George Bailey? What's he want?
I don't know.
What do you want?
Me? Not a thing.
I just came in to get warm.
He's making violent love to me, Mother.
and don't you leave the house, either!
from New York tonight.
You know, I didn't come here to...
-I don't know. You tell me.
that has all the answers. You tell me.
-That's where I'm going.
in the first place.
-Good night!
Mary! Mary! The telephone. It's Sam.
I'll get it.
that you couldn't hear?
Mary, he's waiting.
Hello?
Forgot my hat.
Hee-haw! Hello, Sam, how are you?
Gee, it's good to hear your voice again.
Well, that's awfully sweet of you, Sam.
George Bailey.
You mean old mossback George?
Yes, old mossback George.
Hee-haw! Put him on.
Wait just a minute. I'll call him. George!
you idiot.
He does so. He asked for him.
George, Sam wants to speak to you.
Hi, Sam.
Hey, a fine pal you are.
What're you trying to do, steal my girl?
What do you mean?
Nobody's trying to steal anybody's girl.
Here... Here's Mary.
I want to talk to both of you.
Tell Mary to get on the extension.
-I am not!
We can both hear. Come here.
We're listening, Sam.
that's gonna make us all rich.
that night in Martini's bar
about making plastics out of soybeans?
-Shut up, will you?
Out of soybeans.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Soybeans, yeah.
Well, listen, Dad snapped up the idea,
a factory outside of Rochester.
How do you like that?
Rochester? Well, why Rochester?
Can you think of anything better?
Just why not right here?
and machinery works?
he can get that for a song.
And all the labor he wants, too.
when they closed down.
That so? Well, I'll tell him.
Hey, that sounds great.
Oh, baby, I knew you'd come through.
Mary, you're in on this, too.
Now listen. Have you got any money?
Money? Yeah... Well, a little.
Well, now, listen.
into our stock, do you hear?
And, George, I may have a job for you,
to that broken-down Building and Loan.
since radio,
on the ground floor.
Oh, Mary. Mary?
I'm here.
Would you tell that guy
of a lifetime, do you hear?
The chance of a lifetime!
He says it's the chance of a lifetime.
Now you listen to me.
and I don't want any ground floors.
ever, to anyone.
You understand that?
I want to do what I want to do.
And you're... And you're...
-George, George, George.
Oh, Mary.
Oh, dear. Oh, dear. Oh, dear.
Mary...
Here they come! Here they come!
Goodbye, George!
Goodbye!
First Harry, now George.
Annie, we're just two old maids now.
You speak for yourself, Miss B.
see a stranger around here, it's me.
There's somebody driving this cab.
Bert the cop sent this over.
to Happyland on the bubbles.
Oh, look at this. Old Bert. Champagne!
on this here now honeymoon?
Where are we going? Look at this.
Here, come on, count it, Mary.
I feel like a bootlegger's wife. Look.
We're gonna shoot the works.
A whole week in Bermuda.
the oldest champagne,
and the prettiest wife.
That does it! Then what?
-After that, who cares?
That does it, come here. Come here.
but there's something funny
at the bank, George.
all the earmarks of being a run.
in the bank, you better hurry.
George, let's not stop. Let's go!
Just a minute, dear.
-I'll be back in a minute, Mary.
Mrs. Thompson, how are you?
can't you get in?
What is this, Uncle Billy? A holiday?
George.
That's right. Just come on in.
Look out, you.
Now, look, why don't you all sit down?
There are a lot of seats over there.
Just make yourselves at home.
George, can I see you a minute?
-I just did, but they said you left.
This is a pickle.
How did it start?
How does a thing like this ever start?
-When?
I handed over all our cash.
-Every cent of it,
-Holy mackerel!
and closed the doors.
I... I...
The whole town's gone crazy.
Yeah, hello?
George, it's Potter.
Hello?
that you've closed your doors.
Is that true?
Oh, well, I'm very glad to hear that.
Do you need any police?
Police? What for?
sometimes, you know.
to help in this crisis.
sufficient funds to meet their needs.
and then reopen.
He just took over the bank.
I may lose a fortune,
to guarantee your people, too.
to bring their shares over here,
and I will pay 50 cents on the dollar.
You never miss a trick, do you, Potter?
Well, you're gonna miss this one.
you will never reopen.
George, was it a nice wedding?
Gosh, I wanted to be there.
Yeah.
You can take this one off now.
isn't as black as it appeared.
I have some news for you, folks.
I was just talking to old man Potter,
at the bank.
The bank's gonna reopen next week.
But, George, I got my money here.
Did he guarantee this place?
We don't need Potter over here.
Then, I'll take mine now.
No, but you're...
You're thinking of this place all wrong,
The money's not here.
That's right next to yours.
and Mrs. Macklin's house
and 100 others.
the money to build,
to you as best they can.
foreclose on them?
and $242 isn't going to break anybody.
Okay, Tom. All right.
You'll get your money in 60 days.
Sixty days?
when you bought your shares.
-No.
Well, I did.
on the dollar for every share you've got.
-Yes, cash!
Well, what do you say?
to your original agreement.
Now, give us 60 days on this.
-Are you going to go to Potter's?
Better to get half than nothing.
Tom! Tom!
Randall! Now, Randall, wait! Wait.
I beg of you not to do this thing.
of this Building and Loan,
another decent house built in this town.
He's already got charge of the bank.
He got the department stores.
Well, it's very simple.
on his business, that's why.
to keep you living in his slums
and paying the kind of rent he decides.
of those Potter houses, didn't you?
Well, have you forgotten?
for that broken-down shack?
year when things weren't going so well
and you couldn't make your payments.
did you?
let you keep it?
what's happening here?
Don't you see what's happening?
Potter's buying, and why?
That's why.
He's picking up some bargain.
this thing all right.
We've got to stick together, though.
We've got to have faith in each other.
in over a year, and I need money.
until the bank opens?
-I need cash.
I can't feed my kids on faith.
How much do you need?
Hey! I got $2,000.
This'll tide us over till the bank reopens.
-$242.
until the bank reopens.
I'll take $242.
-That'll close my account.
Your account's still here. That's a loan.
-I got $300 here, George.
till the bank opens? What do you need?
Well, I suppose $20.
Thanks, Ed. That's fine.
how much do you want?
But it's your own money, George.
How much do you want?
-$20, fine.
-You don't have to sign anything.
That's okay.
-Could I have $17.50?
you can have it. You got 50 cents?
-We're gonna make it, George.
-They'll never close us up today!
...five, four, three, two,
one, bingo!
We made it.
We've still got 2 bucks left.
Let's celebrate!
Get some glasses, Tilly.
-Call us Rockefellers.
great big important simoleons here.
We'll save them for seed. A toast.
and to Papa Dollar,
Building and Loan in business,
you better have a family real quick.
-I wish they were, too.
and see what happens.
Close the door.
Folks, folks, wedding cigars.
Wedding. Holy mackerel, I'm married.
Where's Mary? Mary! Poor...
Well, the train's gone.
with his taxicab.
George, there's a call for you.
on the phone?
She's probably over at her mother's.
Mrs. Bailey is on the phone.
I don't want Mrs. Bailey. I want my wife.
Here, I'll take it in here.
Mary. Hello. Listen, dear, I'm sorry.
Huh? Come home? What home?
Whose home is that?
The Waldorf Hotel, huh?
and the company won't like this.
to get a ticket next week?
You got any romance in you?
-Liver pills.
on their honeymoon?
beautiful places,
places George wants to go.
Hey, Bert. Here he comes.
He's coming.
-The groom, idiot.
Come on. Get that ladder.
What are they, ducks?
-All right, all right.
-I'm hurrying.
Hiya... Good evening, sir.
Welcome home, Mr. Bailey.
Well, I'll be...
Mary. Mary, where did you...
Oh, Mary.
some windows in this old house?
This is what I wished for.
You're wonderful.
-Rent?
-What's that?
I own the house.
I own my own house.
in this Potter's Field.
-Mary, come on, bring the baby.
I feel like a queen.
-Oh, thank you, Mr. Bailey. Thank you.
All right, kids, here. Here, get in here.
Get right up on the seat there.
-Here, now, get the dog, now. That's it.
-Everybody!
All in!
Bye-bye! Bye-bye!
All in?
Mr. and Mrs. Martini, welcome home.
he's always making a speech.
Hee-haw!
-Oh, who cares.
may never know hunger.
Salt. That life may always have flavor.
may reign forever.
Enter the Martini castle.
it's no skin off my nose.
I'm just your little rent collector.
this Bailey Park anymore.
Look at it.
to see you, sir.
Go on.
houses stuck here and there.
buttercups, daisies.
I used to hunt rabbits there myself.
Look at it today.
you ever saw,
who used to pay rent to you.
Mr. Employer, is becoming just that.
those David and Goliath wisecracks.
Oh, they are, are they?
the Baileys never made a dime out of it.
The Baileys were all chumps.
Every one of these homes is worth
the Building and Loan to build.
-You are not me.
As I say, it's no skin off my nose,
this bright young man
George Bailey for a job.
a boil on my neck long enough.
-Come in here.
to take a look at the new factory,
drive on down to Florida.
have your friends join us?
drive down with us, huh?
Oh, I'm afraid I couldn't get away, Sam.
to the old grindstone, eh?
on the ground floor in plastics,
and he turned me down cold.
-I'm not rubbing it in.
Well, I guess we better run along.
-Nice meeting you, too.
-Goodbye, George.
See you in the funny papers.
-Bye, Sam. Have fun.
-Florida!
-Hee-haw.
Thank you, sir.
-You like it?
I'll send you a box.
Well, I...
I suppose I'll find out sooner or later,
did you want to see me about?
so much about you.
and most people hate me.
so that makes it all even.
You know just as well as I do
in this town
but the Bailey Building and Loan.
years I've been trying to get control of it.
Or kill it. But I haven't been able to do it.
You have been stopping me.
In fact, you have beaten me, George,
can tell you, that takes some doing.
for instance.
that kept our heads.
I saved all the rest.
you stole all the rest.
George, the suckers.
Now, I have stated my side very frankly.
Now let's look at your side.
making, say, $40 a week.
-$45.
$45.
your mother and paying your bills,
if you skimp.
won't even be able to save the $10.
was a common, ordinary yokel,
I'd say he was doing fine.
ordinary yokel.
ambitious young man,
who hates the Building and Loan
almost as much as I do.
out on his own ever since he was born.
of the crowd, mind you.
A young man who has to sit by
because he's trapped.
trapped into frittering his life away,
to a lot of garlic eaters.
or do I exaggerate?
-My point?
-Hire me?
run my properties.
at $20,000 a year.
$20,000 a year?
in the nicest house in town,
buying your wife a lot of fine clothes,
to New York a year,
maybe once in a while Europe.
would you, George?
Would I?
around here, are you?
You remember me?
-George Bailey.
whose ship has just come in.
to climb aboard.
Holy mackerel.
Well, how about the Building and Loan?
are you afraid of success?
at $20,000 a year, starting today.
Is it a deal, or isn't it?
Well, Mr. Potter, I...
at the chance but I... I just...
to give me 24 hours to think it over?
Sure, sure, sure.
and talk about it to your wife.
I'd like to do that.
I'll draw up the papers.
-Okay, George?
Okay, Mr. Potter.
now wait a minute, here.
I don't have to talk to anybody.
No, doggone it!
and you spin your little webs,
revolves around you and your money.
Well, it doesn't, Mr. Potter.
In the whole vast configuration of things,
but a scurvy little spider.
You...
And that goes for you, too!
And it goes for you, too!
in the nicest house in town,
buying your wife a lot of fine clothes,
a couple of times a year,
maybe Europe once in a while.
I know what I'm gonna do tomorrow
and the year after that.
of this crummy little town off my feet,
and I'm gonna see the world.
I'm gonna build air fields.
100 stories high.
I'm gonna build a bridge a mile long.
What, you want the moon?
I'll throw a lasso around it
and pull her down for you.
Won't you come out tonight?
Won't you come out tonight
And
-Hi.
Mary Hatch,
did you ever marry a guy like me?
To keep from being an old maid.
married Sam Wainwright
and anybody else in town.
to marry anybody else in town.
I want my baby to look like you.
You didn't even have a honeymoon.
I promised you...
-My baby.
Your... Your...
Mary, you on the nest?
-Lassoes a stork!
What is it, a boy or a girl?
that George never leaves Bedford Falls.
-Mary had her baby, a boy.
Then she had another one, a girl.
Day after day she worked away,
into a home.
George came back late from the office.
Potter was bearing down hard.
Then came a war.
joined the Red Cross and sewed.
but still found time to run the USO.
in plastic hoods for planes.
Potter became head of the draft board.
One-A.
Gower and Uncle Billy sold war bonds.
in North Africa, got the Silver Star.
parachuted into France.
the Remagen Bridge.
Harry...
Harry Bailey topped them all.
A Navy flier, he shot down 15 planes,
to crash into a transport full of soldiers.
-George?
Four-F on account of his ear,
of Bedford Falls.
Now, hold on! Hold on! Hold on now!
Don't you know there's a war on?
Air raid warden.
Paper drives.
Scrap drives.
Rubber drives.
he wept and prayed.
On VJ Day, he wept and prayed again.
what happened today.
Yes, sir.
about 10:00 a.m.
Bedford Falls time...
Hey, Ernie. Look at that.
It's gonna snow again.
Look at the headlines. The President...
That's marvelous.
Commander Harry Bailey!
the second page.
Now, look, this is for you.
-Okay.
-See you again.
Be sure you spell the name right.
Extra! Read all about it!
on long-distance from Washington.
Harry! What do you know about that!
It's okay, isn't it?
Of course it is for a hero.
Harry!
a son of a gun. Congratulations.
How's Mother standing it? She did?
What do you know?
with the President's wife.
Wait till Martha hears about this.
-What'd they have to eat?
Harry,
in the town for you.
Oh, they are?
this afternoon.
In a plane?
What? Uncle Billy?
-He stopped at the bank first.
But look, now, tell me about it.
-What?
-What man?
Bank examiner.
will you?
I'll be right back.
-Harry.
-Carter, bank examiner.
-Merry Christmas.
We're all excited around here.
the Congressional Medal of Honor.
-Well, I guess they do those things.
-Good year?
Mr. Carter, we're broke.
Yeah, very funny.
come right in here, Mr. Carter.
when you okay reverse charges
on personal long-distance calls.
-No, no.
You just hold on, there.
I'd like to finish with you by tonight.
in Elmira with my family.
I don't blame you at all, Mr. Carter.
Just step right in here. We'll fix you up.
December 24.
$8,000.
-Merry Christmas.
What's the news?
wins Congressional Medal."
That couldn't be one of the Bailey boys.
now can you, Mr. Potter?
feel about that?
Very jealous. Very jealous.
He only lost three buttons off his vest.
slacker George would've gotten
two of these medals if he had gone.
-Yes.
like George had to stay at home.
in Germany and Japan.
-Good morning, Horace.
-Huh?
-What?
to make a deposit?
Oh, sure, sure I am.
to bring the money with you.
Oh, shucks, I knew I had.
How about that finger there?
Well, I...
Bailey.
Take me back there. Hurry up.
Come on, look sharp.
Take me back.
I got those books for you here.
Oh, hello, Vi.
George, can I see you for a second?
Go on in the office there.
He's on the telephone.
Long distance, Washington.
Hey, here's Harry on the phone.
remember? Harry.
-Hurry up.
Yes, Harry, yes, everything's fine.
I ought to have my head examined.
$8,000. It's got to be somewhere.
Here you are.
Character?
If I had any character, I'd...
your hometown and start all over again.
No, George, don't.
Here now, you're broke, aren't you?
-What do you want to do,
hock your furs and that hat?
You want to walk to New York?
for meals and rent up there,
in Bedford Falls.
-No, that's a loan, now.
That's my business, Building and Loan.
Good luck to you.
I'm glad I know you, George Bailey.
-Yeah, yeah, sure, I will.
once in a while.
-Merry Christmas, George.
-Oh, Mr. Carter, I'm sorry.
Uncle Billy in there?
Yeah, he's in his office.
What's going on?
The bank examiner's here.
-Yeah. He wants the accounts payable...
What's the matter with you?
Come here.
Eustace.
-Come here a minute.
with any cash last night?
before he closed up.
Now, look, did you buy anything?
-All right, all right.
since you left the house.
-Come on.
in your pocket?
Yeah, maybe, maybe.
We've got to find that money!
-Uncle Billy, look,
to happen if we don't find it?
Listen to me.
here in the house?
Someplace you hide the money?
I've gone over the whole house,
since I lost Laura.
Listen to me, listen to me! Think, think!
I can't think anymore. It hurts.
you silly, stupid old fool?
Do you realize what this means?
and prison!
That's what it means.
Well, it's not going to be me.
Hello, darling.
-Hello, Daddy.
How do you like it?
-Bless you!
Did you bring the wreath?
the Christmas wreath?
What wreath?
for the window.
No. I left it at the office.
-Yeah, it just started.
-Left them at the office.
What's the matter?
Everything's all right.
You can help me get this star up.
Way up at the top. There. That's it.
right there. Right there.
We're famous, George.
about the parade, the banquet.
Your mother's so excited. She...
Must she keep playing that?
for the party tonight, Daddy.
till midnight and sing Christmas carols.
Can you sing, Daddy?
Better hurry and shave.
-Families.
I don't want the families over here.
while I finish dinner.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
-Oh, yeah.
for the Baileys.
have a new car. You should see it.
Isn't it good enough for you?
Yes, Daddy.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
-I burped.
All right, darling, you're excused.
and see if little Zuzu wants anything.
-Oh, she's just got a cold. She's in bed.
Caught it coming home from school.
and she didn't want to crush it,
so she didn't button up her coat.
-It's just a cold.
-The doctor?
-Yes, I called him right away.
He says it's nothing to worry about.
What is it?
She'll be all right.
Of course, it's this old house.
we don't all have pneumonia.
Might as well be living in a refrigerator.
to live here in the first place
crummy old town?
-Wrong! Everything's wrong.
Why do we have to have all these kids?
-I don't know. Ask your mother.
-I'm going up to see Zuzu.
He told me to write a play for tomorrow.
F-r-a-n-k-i-n...
Hi, Daddy!
-I won a flower.
Where do you think you're going?
I want to give my flower a drink.
Now, give Daddy the flower.
I'll give it a drink.
Now, here.
Look, Daddy!
Paste it!
Yeah, all right, all right. Give it here.
Now, we'll paste this together here.
There. There it is. Good as new.
Now, give the flower a drink.
Now, will you do something for me?
-Will you try to get some sleep?
I want to look at my flower.
and then you can dream about it,
and it'll be a whole garden.
It will?
-Telephone!
I'll get it.
Hello?
Yes, this is Mrs. Bailey.
I'm sure she'll be all right.
that she ought to be out of bed
in time to have her Christmas dinner.
-Yes.
Let me speak to her.
Hello. Hello, Mrs. Welch?
This is George Bailey. I'm Zuzu's father.
are you, anyway?
sending her home like that, half naked?
with pneumonia on account of you?
-Is this the sort of thing we pay taxes for
to have teachers like you?
our kids home without any clothes on?
aren't the best-dressed kids.
any decent clothes...
That stupid...
Hello, Mrs. Welch. I want to apologize...
Hello? Hello.
-I'll hang her up!
-What is that?
Hello! Who's this?
Oh, Mr. Welch?
Okay, that's fine, Mr. Welch.
what I really think of your wife.
George, stop it.
Will you get out and let me handle this?
Hello? Hello? What?
Oh, you will, huh?
you think you're man enough, you...
Hello! Any...
Dad, how do you spell "hallelujah"?
What do you think I am, a dictionary?
Tommy, stop that! Stop it!
that silly tune yet?
Now stop it! Stop it!
I'm sorry, Mary.
Janie, I'm sorry.
You go on and practice.
Pete, I owe you an apology, too.
I'm sorry.
-Nothing, Daddy.
What's the matter with everybody?
Now, go on, play!
Oh, Daddy!
torture the children? Why don't you...
Mary...
Bedford 247, please.
-Yes, Pete.
-Yes, Janie, pray very hard.
-You, too, Tommy.
Hello? Uncle Billy?
I'm in trouble, Mr. Potter.
I need help.
my company's short in their accounts.
The bank examiner got there today.
I've got to raise $8,000 immediately.
to talk to you about?
-Yes.
from your Building and Loan.
from the D.A.'s office, too.
He's looking for you.
Help me, won't you, please?
to my family?
any interest,
if you still want the Building and Loan...
a slight discrepancy in the books?
There's nothing wrong with the books.
I can't find it anywhere.
-Yes, sir.
-No, sir. I didn't want the publicity.
-They're going to believe that one.
What've you been doing, George?
with the company's money?
No, sir. No, sir, I haven't.
Is it a woman, then?
you've been giving money to Violet Bick.
What?
but why did you come to me?
and ask him for the money?
I can't get a hold of him. He's in Europe.
Well, what about all your other friends?
Mr. Potter. You know that.
that can help me.
I've suddenly become quite important.
would I have, George?
-No, sir.
Collateral of any kind?
a $15,000 policy.
-Five hundred dollars.
Five hundred dollars?
And you ask me to lend you $8,000?
Look at you. You used to be so cocky.
and conquer the world.
frustrated old man.
frustrated young man?
A miserable little clerk,
on your hands and knees
and begging for help.
No securities, no stocks, no bonds.
little $500 equity
in a life insurance policy.
You're worth more dead than alive.
you love so much
and ask them to let you have $8,000?
You know why?
out of town on a rail.
what I'm going to do for you, George.
Since the state examiner is still here,
of the Building and Loan,
a warrant for your arrest.
manipulation, malfeasance.
All right, George, go ahead.
You can't hide in a little town like this.
Yeah, Bill? This is Potter.
Merry Christmas! Glad you come!
How about some of that good spaghetti?
We got everything.
Oh, God.
Dear Father in Heaven,
I'm not a praying man,
and you can hear me,
show me the way.
I'm at the end of my rope. I...
Show me the way, O God.
Want somebody to take you home?
Why you drink so much, my friend?
This is Christmas Eve.
Bailey? Which Bailey?
This is Mr. George Bailey.
like that, you'll get worse!
She cried for an hour!
your stupid kids how to read and write,
-You get out of here, Mr. Welch!
Now, wait, I want to pay for my drink.
You get out of here quick!
-You hit my best friend! Get out!
-Who was that?
He gone. No worry. He name is Welch.
-Oh, Welch.
That's what I get for praying.
You hear that, Nick?
Yes, you bet.
Oh, here it is.
don't go this way, Mr. Bailey.
-No, no, you no feel so good.
-I'm all right.
Please no go away, please!
What do you think you're doing?
My great-grandfather planted this tree!
Hey, you! Hey, you!
Get this car out of here!
Look where you're going.
Help!
Help! Help!
Help! Help! Help! Help!
to get some stylish underwear.
on my last birthday.
I passed away in it.
Oh, Tom Sawyer's drying out, too.
Mark Twain's writing now.
How did you happen to fall in?
I jumped in to save George.
You what? To save me?
You didn't go through with it, did you?
-Suicide.
to commit suicide around here.
where I come from, too.
-Heaven.
That's why I jumped in.
you'd try to save me.
and that's how I saved you.
Very funny.
Your lip's bleeding, George.
in answer to a prayer a little bit ago.
I'm the answer to your prayer.
That's why I was sent down here.
-Oh, I know all about you.
from a little boy.
a mind reader or something?
No.
-Clarence Oddbody, AS2.
Oddbody?
AS2? What's that, AS2?
Angel Second Class.
Cheerio, my good man.
Oh, brother.
Gee whiz.
put in those drinks.
What did you say just a minute ago?
Why'd you want to save me?
I'm your guardian angel.
I wouldn't be a bit surprised.
of killing yourself for money, $8,000.
How do you know that?
I know everything about you.
like the kind of an angel I'd get.
What happened to your wings?
That's why I'm an Angel Second Class.
I don't know whether I'd like it very much
with an angel without any wings.
and you'll help me, won't you?
Sure, sure.
-By letting me help you.
Yes. Only one way you can help me.
8,000 bucks on you, do you?
We don't use money in heaven.
Oh, yeah, that's right, I keep forgetting.
-Oh, tut, tut, tut.
I found it out a little late.
I'm worth more dead than alive.
I won't get my wings with that attitude.
If it hadn't been for you...
everybody'd be a lot better off.
My wife and my kids and my friends.
and haunt somebody else, will you?
I've got my job...
Oh, shut up, will you?
Oh, this isn't gonna be so easy.
would make everyone feel happier, eh?
Well, I don't know. I guess you're right.
if I'd never been born at all.
-I said I wish I'd never been born.
Oh, you mustn't say things like that.
That's an idea.
What do you think?
Yeah, that'll do it.
All right.
You've never been born.
to make all that fuss about it!
What did you say?
You haven't a care in the world.
no $8,000 to get,
with the Sheriff.
-Sure, you can hear out of it.
Well, that's the doggonedest thing.
since I was a kid.
in that cold water.
Your lip stopped bleeding, too, George.
What's happening?
It stopped snowing out here, didn't it?
What's happened here?
is a couple of good stiff drinks.
You want a drink?
soon as these clothes of ours are dry...
The clothes are dry.
Stove's hotter than I thought.
We'll stroll up to my car and get...
Oh, I'm sorry. I'll stroll. You fly.
I can't fly. I haven't got my wings.
Yeah, that's right.
What's the matter?
and it isn't here.
-Well, I had a car, and it was right here.
I guess somebody moved it.
-Oh, say, hey, where's my car?
-My car, my car.
that ran into your tree.
-What do you mean, what tree?
This tree. Here, I ran into it.
Cut a big gash in the side of it there.
You had me worried.
One of the oldest trees in Pottersville.
Pottersville?
Why, you mean Bedford Falls.
Don't you think I know where I live?
What's the matter with you?
Well, I guess I just...
Either I'm off my nut or he is or you are.
It isn't me.
up at Martini's.
-Clarence.
Clarence. Clarence.
Martini is a friend of mine.
There's a place to sit down. Sit down.
-Want a martini?
Where is he?
You want a drink or don't you?
will you, and quick, huh?
Okay.
-I was just thinking.
It's been so long since I...
waiting for you to make up your mind.
That's a good man.
I was just thinking
of a flaming rum punch.
not nearly cold enough.
Wait a minute. Wait a minute. I got it.
and light on the cloves.
Off with you, me lad, and be lively!
we serve hard drinks in here
for men who want to get drunk fast.
around to give the joint atmosphere.
to slip you my left for a convincer?
What's he talking about?
just give him the same as mine.
-Okay.
I never saw Nick act like that before.
from now on.
Oh, yeah.
you worry me, you know.
-No.
You don't, huh?
No wonder you jumped in the river.
so I could get my wings.
-Made what?
that some angel's just got his wings.
better not mention
getting your wings around here.
Why? Don't they believe in angels?
Yeah, they believe in them.
when they see one?
Oh, he never grew up. He's...
-Two hundred and ninety-three,
next May.
That does it. Out, you two pixies!
Go through the door or out the window.
-Now, that's another thing.
calling me Nick?
Well, Nick, that's your name.
I don't know you from Adam's off ox.
Come here, come here.
panhandling around here, huh?
Mr. Gower.
What... What did...
Mr. Gower, look, this is George Bailey.
-No.
No.
Throw him out. Throw him out.
Mr. Gower! Hey, what is...
Isn't that Mr. Gower, the druggist?
for me not to like you.
for poisoning a kid.
you must be a jailbird yourself.
to the door?
Sure. This way, gentlemen.
Stay out.
Get me! I'm giving out wings!
you were not there to stop Gower
into the capsules.
I remember distinctly...
Hey, what's going on around here?
What...
Why, this ought to be Martini's place.
Look, who are you?
I'm your guardian angel.
Yeah, yeah, I know. You told me that.
What, are you a hypnotist?
No. Of course not.
all these strange things here?
It's because you were not born.
-You're nobody. You have no identity.
My name's George Bailey.
There is no George Bailey.
no driver's license,
no 4-F card, no insurance policy.
They're not there, either.
-Zuzu's petals.
You've been given a great gift, George,
would be like without you.
Wait a minute here.
I'm having.
So long, mister. I'm going home.
-Shut up! Cut it out!
That's what I think. You're screwy.
I'm seeing things here.
and see my wife and family.
And I'm going home alone.
How am I doing, Joseph?
Thanks.
No, I didn't have a drink.
the Building and Loan move to?
Building and what?
It was up there.
They went out of business years ago.
That sailor's a liar!
I know every big shot in this town!
and I'll have you kicked off the beat.
Hey, Violet!
Hey, hey! Listen. That's Violet Bick.
-I know that girl!
Take a walk. Beat it.
Hey, Ernie! Ernie.
I'm going off my nut.
Where do you live?
don't you start pulling that stuff.
Now hurry up.
-Yeah, yeah, hurry up. Zuzu's sick.
-All right. All right.
now straighten me out here.
or something. Listen to me.
Now, you are Ernie Bishop,
with your wife and kid?
-You seen my wife?
I've been to your house 100 times.
I live in a shack in Potter's Field,
and took the kid,
before in my life, see?
Just get me home!
-Of course it's the place.
for 20 years.
-I don't know.
He's bats.
Mary. Mary!
Where are you?
You have no children.
What have you done with them?
No fast moves.
Come on out here, both of you.
-Back this.
Where's Mary? Where's my kids?
-Come on, come on.
What's the matter with you two guys?
You were here on my wedding night.
stood out there on the porch
-Think I'd better be going.
Look, now, why don't you be a good kid,
and we'll take you in to a doctor?
-Bert, no, listen to me.
to my mother's house?
He says he's an angel.
-I hate to do this to you, bud, but...
Run, George! Run, George! Run!
-Oh, shut up.
Oh, Joseph! Joseph!
I had him right here.
I need a drink.
Help me find him.
Well?
Mother.
Mother? What do you want?
Mother, this is George.
I thought sure you'd remember me.
George who?
there's no vacancy.
Something terrible's happened to me.
Something's happened to everybody.
and keep me here until I get over it.
Get over what? I don't take in strangers
by somebody I know.
Your brother-in-law, Uncle Billy.
-Well, sure I do.
-Today over at his house.
It's a lie.
ever since he lost his business.
that's where you belong.
Strange, isn't it?
touches so many other lives.
he leaves an awful hole, doesn't he?
I've heard of things like this.
or something.
I'll get out of it.
I know how, too. I...
The last man I talked to,
started happening to me, was Martini.
You know where he lives?
He lives in Bailey Park.
-No, I'm not sure of anything anymore.
All I know is this should be Bailey Park.
-You weren't here to build them.
broke through the ice
and was drowned at the age of nine.
That's a lie. Harry Bailey went to war.
Medal of Honor.
of every man on that transport.
Every man on that transport died.
Harry wasn't there to save them,
to save Harry.
You really had a wonderful life.
it would be to throw it away?
-Yes, George?
-Oh, well, I can't...
but tell me, where is she?
tell me where my wife is.
-Please, Clarence, tell me where she is.
-Where is she?
She's an old maid. She never married.
Where is she?
She's just about to close up the library!
for me to get my wings.
Mary!
Mary! Mary!
What's happened to us?
I don't know you. Let me go!
Please, Mary, help me.
Where's our kids? I need you, Mary.
Help me, Mary!
Mary! Let me go!
Help! It's a wild man!
Somebody stop him!
Tom! Ed! Charlie!
That's my wife!
-No, you don't.
Somebody call the police.
with a bottle.
You need a straightjacket.
Clarence!
Get out of here!
-Right, that's you!
Stand back!
Clarence!
Clarence! Clarence!
Help me, Clarence!
Get me back!
I don't care what happens to me.
Get me back to my wife and kids.
Help me, Clarence, please.
I want to live again.
Please, God, let me live again.
Hey, George!
George!
You all right. Hey, what's the matter?
or I'll hit you again! Get out of here!
are you yelling for, George?
You...
George? Bert, do you know me?
Know you? You kidding?
trying to find you.
down there, and I thought maybe you...
Are you sure you're all right?
What did...
My mouth's...
Zuzu's petals. Zuzu... There they are!
Bert! What do you know about that?
-Well, Merry Christmas.
Mary! Mary!
Hello, Bedford Falls!
Merry Christmas!
-Merry Christmas!
Merry Christmas, George.
Merry Christmas, movie house!
Merry Christmas, emporium!
you wonderful old Building and Loan!
Hey, Merry Christmas, Mr. Potter!
Happy New Year to you in jail!
Go on home. They're waiting for you.
Mary! Mary!
Mary!
How are you?
-I know, $8,000.
George, I've got a little paper here.
I'll bet it's a warrant for my arrest.
Isn't it wonderful? I'm going to jail!
Where's Mary?
old drafty house.
Mary! Mary!
Mary.
Have you seen my wife?
Merry Christmas, Daddy.
Kids! Pete!
Kids! Janie!
Janie! Tommy!
Oh, I could eat you up.
Where's your mother?
-With Uncle Billy.
-Zuzu!
How do you feel?
-Not a smidge of...
-Hello.
-Mary! Mary!
George, darling. Where have you been?
-Mary.
Let me touch you. Are you real?
George, George.
what's happened to me.
You've no idea what happened...
Come on downstairs, quick.
-All right.
Come on.
Come on in here now.
by the tree.
Don't move.
Who's gonna come?
I hear them coming now.
George, it's a miracle. It's a miracle.
-What's happening?
-Who, Daddy?
Everybody, in here.
George.
Here's everything right here.
Mary did it, George! Mary did it!
you were in trouble,
collecting money.
Didn't ask any questions.
"George in trouble? Then count me in."
-You never saw anything like it.
...another run on the bank?
Here you are, George. Merry Christmas.
There we are.
The line forms on the right.
More coming, George.
Merry Christmas, and God bless you.
Merry Christmas.
-Merry Christmas.
Martini! Step right up here.
I busted the jukebox, too.
Oh, Mr. Gower!
of my charge accounts.
I changed my mind.
Violet Bick.
Oh, Annie! Annie!
for a divorce,
if ever I get a husband.
Merry Christmas.
I got the faculty all up and out of bed.
Here's something for you to play with.
if it wasn't for you, George.
Quiet, everybody. Quiet, quiet.
Now, get this, it's from London.
"Mr. Gower cabled you need cash. Stop.
to advance you up to $25,000. Stop.
Sam Wainwright."
And Mr. Martini. How about some wine?
Hark the herald angels sing
Glory to the newborn king
Peace on earth and mercy mild
God and sinners reconciled
Joyful, all ye nations rise
Join the triumph of the skies
With angelic host proclaim
Christ is born in Bethlehem
Harry Bailey!
George, you old son of a gun.
Harry. Harry.
Looks like I got here too late.
just as quick as I could.
in a blizzard.
in New York?
as soon as I got Mary's telegram.
Good idea, Ernie. A toast
the richest man in town!
Should auld acquaintance be forgot
And never brought to mind?
Should auld acquaintance
Be forgot
And days of auld lang syne
Who's that?
from a very dear friend of mine.
Look, Daddy!
an angel gets his wings.
That's right.
Attaboy, Clarence.
Auld lang syne
For auld lang syne, my dear
For auld lang syne
We'll drink a cup of kindness yet